Isaac Parks papers, Inclusive: 1858-1877, Bulk: 1862-1877
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Isaac Parks papers
Inclusive: 1858-1877, Bulk: 1862-1877
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
199
Parks, Isaac
1 box.
The Isaac Parks papers, containing a diary and various letters, are a rare personal look at the Texas home front during the American Civil War and Reconstruction after the war.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Biography/Profile
Isaac Parks, like many men born in the Old South before the Civil War, led a mobile life, always looking for better opportunities. He was born in Monroe County, Georgia, in 1810, and probably married his wife Martha Parks at some point while in Georgia. The Parks had at least one child during his over thirty year stay in Georgia. In 1844, the Parks moved to Chambers County, Alabama, then to Grimes County, Texas, in 1853.
By 1860, right before the Civil War, Isaac and Martha had a prospering farm near Anderson, Grimes County. Isaac, along with other farmers in the area, formed an agricultural society in 1855. He accepted two committee positions, one to write a constitution, and the other on “hillside ditching.” In keeping with his agricultural activities, Isaac may have also set up a cotton gin to process the cotton crop. At some point in the 1860s Isaac also became a pastor for his community. The 1860 population census for that year indicates the Parks had five children at the time, two boys born in Alabama, and a girl and two more boys born in Texas. At the start of the war, Isaac was fifty-one years old, too old to be in the Confederate army, but he was in the nominal Texas militia for Grimes County.
After the war, Isaac continued noting his activities in his diary during Reconstruction in Texas. His diary continues until 1877, the same year that he died in Grimes County at sixty-eight years old. Isaac Parks’ diary and associated letters continue to provide important information about daily life in Civil War Texas, including information on the weather, crops, Parks’ neighbors, and local social occurrences.
Scope and Content
The Isaac Parks papers contain photocopies of typescripts of his diary and correspondence. The diary chronicles Parks's daily activities in Anderson, Texas during the Civil War and Reconstruction, and also provides information on the weather, crops, Parks's neighbors, and social occurrences.
Arrangement
The Isaac Parks papers were organized by type with folder labels prior to this finding aid. A comprehensive finding aid was not available prior to this finding aid.
The collection is arranged in two series: I. Correspondence and II. Diaries.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 199. Acquired 1970-03-25
Related Resources
Related references
Boulware, Narcissa Martin. “Old Dacus, Chapter 7.” Montgomery County News, 2002.
The Texas Baptist. “Report.” 1855 April 2. Newspaper Abstracts. Accessed 2020 April 3.
United States Census. “Isaac Parks.” 1860 and 1870. Heritage Quest Online. Accessed 2020 April 3.
Walker, James Lafayette, C.P. Lumpkin, J.P. Lumpkin. History of the Waco Baptist Association of Texas. Waco, Texas: Byrne-Hill Printing House, 1897.
Westmoreland, Jim, and Grimes County Sons of Confederate Veterans Camp. “Confederate Soldiers Buried in Grimes County, Texas.” Accessed 2020 April 3.
Index Terms
Places
Anderson (Tex.); Grimes County (Tex.); Texas -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Social aspects.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Genres
Correspondence.; Diaries.
- Correspondence, 1858-1877; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains letters to and from Isaac Parks, his brother-in-law E.G. Cabiness, Parks’ daughter-in-law. All letters are typed copies, there are no original letters in this collection. This series is in good condition.
  - Correspondence, 1858-1877 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Diaries, 1862-1865, undated; 2
  General condition: Excellent.
  This series contains Isaac Parks lengthy diary of 151 typed pages. Diary contains much information about his daily life, with entries for nearly every day. Entire diary is a typed copy, there are no original diary pages in this collection. This series is in excellent condition.
  - Isaac Parks (1 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Isaac Parks (2 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Isaac Parks (3 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Isaac Parks (4 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Isaac Parks (5 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Isaac Parks (6 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Isaac Parks (7 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Isaac Parks (8 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Isaac Parks (9 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Isaac Parks (10 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Isaac Parks (11 of 11), 1861-1877 (Box 1, Folder 12)